Suibi Weng: Okay, is Ellen you gonna…
Suibi Weng: Say something, or I just thought…
Suibi Weng: You can install it. Okay, cool.
Suibi Weng: Hello, everyone! Welcome to my doctoral dissertation defense, and… Sorry, let me move my mouse. If I cannot find my mouse, let me know where the mouse is, yeah.
Suibi Weng: Okay, so, these are my committee. Two of them are sitting in the spotlight, and some of them are online now.
Suibi Weng: Okay, my name is Suibi Zhechuan Wang, and you can call me Suibi. I got my CS degree at Datong University in 2012, and then later I got my Interactional Design Master in Taipei Tech in 2014. Now I'm in Atlas.
Suibi Weng: Yay. So, before we jump into today's topic, I want to talk about, how I'm getting here.
Suibi Weng: Yeah, not here, the topic, okay.
Suibi Weng: So, that's from the beginning. So, mixed reality has a long history. In 1968, Yvonne Sutherland introduced one of the earliest headsets, among display, which is the foundation of the mixed reality, sorry, the virtual reality.
Suibi Weng: And throughout 1970 and 1980, VR continues to develop in research lab and simulation system. In 1990, the Boeing company introduced the concept of argument reality.
Suibi Weng: In 1994, Paul Milligram and Fumio Kishino formalized the mixed reality as a part of spectrum between real and virtual world.
Suibi Weng: Then, in the 2010s, the device like Oculog Rift or HTC Vive, those kind of commercialized systems been introduced to the world. And that's when I step into the field.
Suibi Weng: Me, in 2014 and 13, I was in…
Suibi Weng: interactional design, that… there was a workshop which is hosted by Alan and Mark during that time, and we were making an installation, it's like using Vephoria marker, and you can see the ghosts playing a miniature playground, something like that.
Suibi Weng: And then…
Suibi Weng: That's inspired my master thesis is like a virtual object and tangible box, and it will react those virtual soldiers, something like that. Yeah, so you can see, oh, it's moving around.
Suibi Weng: However, during that time, I really didn't…
Suibi Weng: step into, like, VR headset, because it's so expensive, and it's not really impressive, because you can only, like, sing around, and you cannot walk in or interact with, virtual content.
Suibi Weng: Around the same time, I started using one really, interesting device, which is HTC Vite.
Suibi Weng: The very first time I tried it, I was surprised that it's a really interesting experience, because that's the first VR that I can, walking around, interactive with the virtual content, and with the avatar.
Suibi Weng: And it felt, it kind of let me open my imagination of the future of computing, and more importantly, I feel like I can reach out something like previously I cannot reach about.
Suibi Weng: So that's the first time I'm using, HTC Vi, I was so surprised.
Suibi Weng: And then, after I started working on many devices, so…
Suibi Weng: Before I joined the program, I was an engineer, I'm working on a lot of industry devices and commercial devices, like MR, ARXR, and installations. And also, I am a teacher. I teach people how to make their own immersive experience.
Suibi Weng: And also, I'm an artist. I'm working with other artists, working in theater, working in the museum to… to help them how to use technology, how to use VR to express their, their… their thought.
Suibi Weng: So, however, I didn't choose the…
Suibi Weng: path that my colleague did, because they opened a studio and making a lot of money. I came to here as a PhD student. And you can see, these three projects actually happen in this floor. So, in here,
Suibi Weng: So this, actually, this room is really… has a special meaning for me. So you can see these two projects. The tape is still there. So…
Suibi Weng: But, okay, back to the presentations. When I start my PhD in CU Boulder.
Suibi Weng: a divisor and other, colleague, they were keeping asking. One question, is like, what is your research question?
Suibi Weng: To be honest.
Suibi Weng: I'm still doing the same thing. So, in that time, I honestly say I didn't know, okay?
Suibi Weng: And then, the second turning point is here.
Suibi Weng: Then in 2022, maybe 23, one day I walk into the Acme Lab.
Suibi Weng: And my colleague, Turing, if, in case you don't know who's Turing is, he's sitting over there.
Suibi Weng: He was doing, like… of…
Suibi Weng: his triple PhD and taking, like, 10 classes in one semester, or something like that.
Suibi Weng: Torin asked me one thing, one thing is, have you tried ChatGPT?
Suibi Weng: And it's… it's really amazing. At the first, I was kind of skeptical with this kind of system, because as an engineer, I think it's not reliable. And also, I have my pride. Like, I am an engineer, some chat box shouldn't take over me, right?
Suibi Weng: But when I try it, I toss my pride right away.
Suibi Weng: I've become fascinated not only because it could help the generating writing.
Suibi Weng: coding and visual assets, like this image, because it provides the same feeling that the first time I wear the VR headset, HTC Vite VR headset. I feel like I can reach out something like previously, I cannot reachable.
Suibi Weng: So that's back into reflecting what I care about as a researcher.
Suibi Weng: Before I was, before I am a researcher, I am an engineer, I care about building systems that are efficient and reliable. As a teacher, I care about people, how to make ideas understandable, collaborate, accessible, and meaningful to others.
Suibi Weng: As an artist, I care about creativity, expression, and embrace… embracing the unexpected possibility in this process.
Suibi Weng: what excites me about Gen AI was it connects all three.
Suibi Weng: It suggests a new way to build a system, lower the barriers for peoples, and open up the new form of creative expressions. And that is what leads me to the core question of this dissertation.
Suibi Weng: is how Gen AI can expand MR beyond SS creations toward interactive collaboration, behavior, authoring, and perceptual transformation. These perspectives come together to today's topic, is Generating Your Reality.
Suibi Weng: Advancing the design of AI-generated user experience in mixed reality.
Suibi Weng: So, this is today's outline. We're gonna jump into the first one.
Suibi Weng: Motivation, okay.
Suibi Weng: So, MR is a really powerful device. They can do creativity, collaboration, and simulation. However, building MR is a really hard, process. You need…
Suibi Weng: Years of training, you'll need experience, and doing a lot of things to doing right, you need a lot of effort. However, generative AI kind of lowered those creations, pipeline, or workflow in other domains.
Suibi Weng: But Gen AI in MR, still facing a lot of challenge in spatial coherence, multimodel interaction, responsiveness, also UX design.
Suibi Weng: So, in this case, this…
Suibi Weng: dissertation argue Gen AI can move MR beyond just creating assets. By this means is, like, we are not creating model and putting to, the MR scene just like that. So.
Suibi Weng: I framed through the four connected ideas. First is iterate co-creation.
Suibi Weng: Creation does not happen just one prompt, one output. It's like we're keeping trying, seeing, and revising, and negotiate the result. The secondly is multimodal interaction. In mixed reality, we're not just
Suibi Weng: typing the prompt in mixed reality. We can use our body, our sketch, or even other spatial information to prompting the generative model.
Suibi Weng: And the third one is AI as a co-creative partner. The AI is not just only a backend creation tool, it can suggest the possibility, transform the scenes, introduce the surprise, and participate in the creative process.
Suibi Weng: process. And the last one is a spatial grounding. The generative result should not just happen on the screen, it should happen in place, and in time, and in a real object.
Suibi Weng: So, I'm gonna introduce my three
Suibi Weng: project, through editing reality, DreamProto, Hypervision, I will show generative AI systems can support creation that unfold through interaction, take the place in physical context, and shaped by both human intent and AI-generated possibility.
Suibi Weng: First… First project, editing reality.
Suibi Weng: Okay.
Suibi Weng: So, a lot of previous work of the, MR system is, like, placing the virtual object in the scenes, but if you want to, like,
Suibi Weng: Modify the real scenes, or modify the real object.
Suibi Weng: in the field, you need… you require a really significant setup, for example, like, setting up multiple, connect, or something like that, to doing the modify. However, generative AI can
Suibi Weng: Try to accelerate, or helping us to doing this kind of editing.
Suibi Weng: So, the direct question we ask is, how can Gen AI support the real-time editing of mixed in the mixed reality?
Suibi Weng: Okay, to address this, I developed Editing Reality, a real-time MR system for on-demand editing of physical world through Gen AI and multimodel interaction. I'm gonna play the video, I know tons of you already seen it, so I'm not gonna play all the things of you.
Suibi Weng: Okay, nevermind. I just saw someone sitting outside. You can sit inside. Okay.
Audio shared by Suibi Weng: Editing Reality supports 8 core features. Generate.
Audio shared by Suibi Weng: Iterate.
Audio shared by Suibi Weng: Reconstruct.
Audio shared by Suibi Weng: Retexture.
Audio shared by Suibi Weng: Sketch-based modeling.
Audio shared by Suibi Weng: Erase?
Audio shared by Suibi Weng: Anchor.
Audio shared by Suibi Weng: And collaboration, each designed to align with users' creative workflows in physical space.
Suibi Weng: Okay, so in the workflow, you see, it's like, I can use prompt, just create my,
Suibi Weng: coffee table over here, or I can changing… retexturing the chair into a leather texture, or reconstruct another sofa, or even erase the plants on the table, and also you can use Sketch to create a 3D model with your prompt.
Suibi Weng: How do we do that? It's, like, the heavy lifting of the generated pipeline is hosting on local machines, and the headsets only take care to placing the object, download the generated content, and receive user's prompt, and send it to the local host.
Suibi Weng: So by this, we actually run through, two studies. One is, like, a workshop study. First, we have, like, 14 participants. It's like a prototype study plan, and we're kind of leading to the 7 design goals, and then that leading to the last, final system
Suibi Weng: Build, implementation, and we use that implementation to, evaluate with the expert, with a expert.
Suibi Weng: And the result actually come out is this framework. After an expert review, I developed a co-creation ecology designer frameworks. The key idea that co-creation in generated MR is not just prompting to AI. It's a situate social and spatial process. Involve users, collaborators.
Suibi Weng: The physical room.
Suibi Weng: and generated artifact and AI system. Because designers are working in MR, they are standing inside a scene, what they are modifying.
Suibi Weng: They can move around, evaluate, scale with their body, and discuss the possibility.
Suibi Weng: and interpretate AI output in a relations to the physical environment. So I describe that process as negotiate intent. Intent is not fixed at a first prompt.
Suibi Weng: But it developed through previewing, revising, and discussing, waiting, moving, and iterating in the space.
Suibi Weng: So this project contributes just not just a system, but also a framework that understanding human-AI co-creation inside a physical space.
Suibi Weng: So, the takeaway is, editing reality is a generative AI, not just a tool. It becomes a co-creative partner that you can talk with and interact with.
Suibi Weng: Users are not simply prompting the model and accepting result, they are negotiating with the system through back-and-forward process, prompt, preview, evaluate, revise, and try again.
Suibi Weng: The mixed reality, the third takeaway is mixed reality is important in this setup because we let users
Suibi Weng: working in the physical space, and they can embody… they can design through their embodied experience. So editing realities show that human-AI co-creation in MR, not only computational, it's spatial, social, and situate.
Suibi Weng: The second project is Dream Proto.
Suibi Weng: If editing reality is focused on editing the world, then DreamProto asks. One question is, what if Gen AI, not just…
Suibi Weng: create… Object, but create interactive.
Suibi Weng: So let's shift the question from what appears in the space to how things act in space.
Suibi Weng: So a lot of generated MR system is, like, of generated assets and putting in a space, which is exactly like editing reality did. However, if I want to generate a virtual
Suibi Weng: severe, and I might… don't care what it looked like, I want it to bounce in, collide with other objects, trigger the particle system, response to the users, even just control the physical devices in the space. How do I do that? So…
Suibi Weng: DreamProto explored how Gen AI can support behavior authoring in mixed reality. The system used prompt and the scene's context to generate not only 3D object, but also a runtime Lua-based behavior.
Suibi Weng: Script that defines how those objects interact with users.
Suibi Weng: So we kind of framed it in the three different, interaction type. So, these two players over here is the user.
Suibi Weng: And usually, the color coding blue is the virtual object. So you can see, the first interaction is user interacts with the generated virtual object, and the virtual object interacted
Suibi Weng: with each other, and then the virtual object will interact with the environment. Yeah.
Suibi Weng: Okay, so I'm gonna show a couple videos that… how we… how we do the development. So that's the first iteration that we just only give… generate a lamp, and LLM kind of defined that, oh, because it's a lamp, so it should have a trigger that I can turn on the light.
Suibi Weng: Something like that. So, in this stage, we didn't really touch how to do the real-time behavior programming, but in the second stage.
Suibi Weng: Here.
Suibi Weng: I'm gonna show… I generate a baseball.
Suibi Weng: And with a baseball falling on the ground, it's a collision happening, so you see the particle is split out, and you can see my baseball bat is kind of adding the force on the base… on the baseball. It's not that good, but you can see. Okay.
Suibi Weng: And the second part is, I generate a UFO, and that the UFO can fly away.
Suibi Weng: Something like that, and following your path. So you can see it has a cosine wave like that, but I don't like this kind of path, so I can call my UFO back.
Suibi Weng: And here has a panel that you can change in the different parameter, which is generated by AI as well.
Suibi Weng: Then you can see the UFO fly closer, and you hit the table, so you can see it flicking around, something like that. So that's the second stage we did with this project, and…
Suibi Weng: Then, continuously, we built another… we did another try, it's like, we built a conversational panel that you can keep prompting the same object and keeping changing the behavior, in this case. So you can see…
Suibi Weng: I just prompting, like, breathing, and you can see that, that, Safir just doing the animations, because LLM thinks breathing is, like, changing the size.
Suibi Weng: Okay. And moreover, keeping prompting, I say, oh, not just only breathing, I want you to fly me, like, circulate paths around me, then I can send you second prompt.
Suibi Weng: Like this.
Suibi Weng: And you can, can see the… the Sophia still breathing, and just, flying around, With me, okay.
Suibi Weng: And the second part is, we're gonna show…
Suibi Weng: the object can interact with each other, so the prompt I gave is, like, if the other object hit you, just changing the color.
Suibi Weng: Yeah, so, just to remind you… remind you again, those, we did not do any coding here, just only using the natural prompt.
Suibi Weng: So it's coming like that.
Suibi Weng: The last one is we can show up… we want to, relay out the virtual object. So I'm gonna relay out this cube, say, this gonna circle… can you relay out, like, a circle? Yeah, something like that.
Suibi Weng: I'm not gonna jump.
Suibi Weng: So you can see the final result actually is here. It will circulate like that just by using LLM to interpret your intent here.
Suibi Weng: So how do we do that? So, basically, DreamProto is a prompt engineering system.
Suibi Weng: That we have a set of instruction and set of the rules over there, and…
Suibi Weng: can kind of interpretate a user's intent, and you generate the object, and you apply a Lua script. And why are we using Lua script? Because this is one of the methods that you can let,
Suibi Weng: game object running in runtime, you have to use Lua script, you cannot use the C-Shop in this context.
Suibi Weng: And you can apply the interaction, particle effect, then you create an interactive object, then the object will come back to the environment, and you will affect the next round of the generations.
Suibi Weng: So the contribution of the Dream Proto, it extended generated MR from assets generation to behavior authoring.
Suibi Weng: It shows that GenAI can act as a behavior scripting layer. It makes interactive MR prototyping more accessible and dynamic, from editing content to authoring interaction.
Suibi Weng: So, takeaway is, the system should not fully automate creation. Instead, it should support a collaboration between AI and generation human intent, which is, like.
Suibi Weng: the system should not, like, oh, I get a prompt lamp, so you should turn on, something like that. You should have a keeping-continue conversation with the system, and you will have the best result.
Suibi Weng: And the second takeaway is that as interactions become more complex, the system should have structure, pipeline can support reacher prompts, and more object, and more behavior, because we are using prompt engineering here, so it has
Suibi Weng: facing a lot of problem, that if I'm gonna fit for scenario A, then I have to fix it a lot of things.
Suibi Weng: But if you change it to scenario B, then I cannot really transfer that, too. So I think for a scalable system, it's necessary, like this kind of generative system. And the third, third one actually is one of the answers. How we fix that is DreamProto is strongest
Suibi Weng: When it's supporting, like, specific…
Suibi Weng: scenario. Rather than making something like a Unity engine in the MR system, we should pick, like, a certain scenario, so that's one of the reasons in dissertation, I kind of say we are going to make an IoT system, in the future.
Suibi Weng: Okay Now, the last project.
Suibi Weng: The third project, is Hypervision.
Suibi Weng: If TrimProto asks how generative AI can generate object and behavior in MR,
Suibi Weng: Hypervision asking a more radical question is, what if generative AI could transform, not only what appears in the space, but how the world itself visually presented to user?
Suibi Weng: So, traditionally, MR still treated real and virtual in separate layers. Even with gen-generated tools, most systems still generate the content in certain things or replacing the things.
Suibi Weng: Hypervision asking one question. What if we transform the presented view itself?
Suibi Weng: How we do that? We introduce the concept of generative re-rendering.
Suibi Weng: Which is take users' path-through view through a diffusion model, and after diffusion model, regenerate it, and you send it back to the headset.
Suibi Weng: Okay.
Suibi Weng: So, idea is illustrated as a perception action loop. User input, virtual, virtual elements, and combined with the physical scenes, processed through a deficient model and returned as a re-rendering view.
Suibi Weng: In these actions, we can say it is a continuous circle of seeing, acting, and re-seeing, because every friend will affect in that next interaction and next decision of your prompting.
Suibi Weng: So, in this case, we proposed, like, five, interactions scenario. First one is re-rendering the virtual object, and re-rendering the physical object, hyper-rendering, and full VR scenes re-rendering, and the last one is the full physical scenes re-rendering.
Suibi Weng: And here's the video. I not… still, I'm not gonna play everything, and I cannot find my mouse. Okay, here.
Suibi Weng: So, after the system build, we run a user study, and I have to explain the user study real quick. So, we compare two different transformation settings, and I'm gonna play this video just to explain real quick. And where's my mouse? Okay.
Suibi Weng: So we…
Suibi Weng: kind of, testing out two different kinds of transformation. So, for example, like, high step is me… it will follow in the RGB input, so you can see the couch still, like, couch, but the lower step is totally… AI just re… reinterpreted everything. So you can… I keep playing this…
Suibi Weng: Here, so you can see there's a difference. And we compare these two conditions and to see how users are feeling, and how they like it.
Suibi Weng: So, the first, the first insight is the trade-off between recognizability and reinterpretation. So, if you're gonna use this system in a, kind of, like.
Suibi Weng: internal design or product design, you will choose a high step, because it's following the, the object's, visual cue, but if you want to build a VR or
Suibi Weng: like, imaginary scenes, then you will choose the lower, lower step. So, user actually didn't mention, like, which one is their favorite. It's, like, both, there's a… has their, their own role in this situation.
Suibi Weng: And the second insight is rapid interaction support ideation. The participant doesn't…
Suibi Weng: That not only won't respond to the final image, they want to quick.
Suibi Weng: to see and try, revisit. So, you can see in the video, it's flicking around, but for participant, that's actually a good thing, because they can see a lot of, lot of different versions, different generation, in the same time, and in the same space. And the third insight is spatial corresponding support, control, and continuity.
Suibi Weng: Participants feel more in control when the generation change and stay connected to the physical space, and with their input.
Suibi Weng: So the takeaway is, actually, a lot of people is, enjoy the uncertainty that
Suibi Weng: introduced by AI. The generated output not only fully predictably, but,
Suibi Weng: a participant doesn't think that's necessarily a problem. Secondly, the system invites user to explore more, so our system mechanism actually led a user to trying out their own scenario, and they defied some scenario that we never think about it.
Suibi Weng: And the last one is user engage with generative regenerative as a co-creative process. So, this system is the part of the creativity process.
Suibi Weng: Okay.
Suibi Weng: That's leading to conclusion.
Suibi Weng: So, to synthesize these three projects, I want to describe how each one expands the roles of generative AI in mixed reality.
Suibi Weng: In editing reality, GenAI acts as a collaborator. It helps users edit the physical world through generation, and with those 8 core features.
Suibi Weng: In DreamProto, generative AI becomes a behavior author. It not only generates what objects look like, it generates what objects act like.
Suibi Weng: In hypervision, generative AI becomes a perceptual meditator.
Suibi Weng: In transform, user pass-through view, changing how the physical world visually presented and interpreted.
Suibi Weng: So, I kind of back to the frameworks I mentioned before. So, each project responds to these ideas in different ways. In editing reality, this project emphasized multimodel interaction and spatial grounding, because users not only design in a separate screen, they are standing inside the space they are modifying.
Suibi Weng: In Dream Proto, AI is a co-creative partner, because the AI participate.
Suibi Weng: in the translate human intent to interactive logic. In hypervision,
Suibi Weng: AI move toward to perceptual transformations. In this project, highlights iteration, spatial grounding, and treat perception as a part of design.
Suibi Weng: Across this project, these ideas become more than just framing, emerge as a design principle for future generative MR systems.
Suibi Weng: Together, these principles show that Gen AI can move beyond, create asset, and toward to more situate, embody, and collaborate for human AI creation.
Suibi Weng: Okay, before… before I end, I want to return the two critical moments of this journal, this journey. So the first one is I…
Suibi Weng: try the HTC VR first time, and the second time is like, I seriously engaged with ChatGPT.
Suibi Weng: Both moments gave me the similar feeling, that they expand my imagination, what the computational future will become, and more importantly, they help me feel like I can reach out something previously unreachable.
Suibi Weng: And this brings me to one of the large beliefs behind this dissertation. The goal of Gen AI, at least for me, is not replace human creativity. It's expand what people can reach, shape, and explore.
Suibi Weng: So, when people are asking, and I mean a lot of people is asking the same question, it's like, is AI gonna replace us? I would say no, AI is not gonna replace us, period.
Suibi Weng: Many generative interactive systems today, they are designed, like, from, with one idea, it's like.
Suibi Weng: you give me one prompt, and I can give you everything. However, for human beings, this… our desire is not enough.
Suibi Weng: Because as a creator, as a builder, and as a maker, our satisfaction does not come from, like, oh, that works. It comes from
Suibi Weng: to saying, wow, I make it work. So that process matter, that exploration matter, and more importantly, the struggling matter.
Suibi Weng: I remember something like, Olympic gold medalist Alysa Liu in the interview saying, I love struggling because struggling made me feel alive.
Suibi Weng: I think that captures something important about creation. We do not want result, we want the experience to reach those unreachable.
Suibi Weng: Generative AI will become more powerful, for sure, in the future, or next week. Okay.
Suibi Weng: So… but the human desire will keep in reach further, and we don't know… we do not only want convenience, we want expression, participations, and the ability to reach out something that's previously unreachable.
Suibi Weng: That's why combination of Gen AI and MR is exciting to me, because it's giving us a new way to shape, question, and create across both physical and virtual world.
Suibi Weng: I hope this research can contribute, even in a small way, for that future. A future that… where people can imagine, build, and explore in a way that previously cannot reach. And thank you.
Suibi Weng: annoying.
Suibi Weng: Okay, acknowledgement. So, I did not write, like, 20-page acknowledgement like my colleague.
Suibi Weng: So, I'm gonna stare in your eyes, if you are in person, I will say I love you, and thank you.
Suibi Weng: No.
Suibi Weng: First of all, hi, committee! So, thank you, Alan,
Suibi Weng: Thank you, Alan. Thank you for me to this program. And, recently, Alan told me one thing, is the HCI community in Taiwan.
Suibi Weng: say, Alan is our Azzo.
Suibi Weng: Azo is Taiwanese great-grandmother. So, it's an honor that working with you, and to be your students, and your kindness. I wish one day I have the same ability to share those things to my student or my colleague.
Suibi Weng: Thank you. Okay.
Suibi Weng: And Tom! Hi, Tom!
Suibi Weng: Thank you, Tom! He's so nice, because…
Suibi Weng: I kinda fucked up with, my com.
Suibi Weng: And the first time, and Tom actually gave me his number. If any problem, just call me, and I did call him.
Suibi Weng: So, thank you, Tom, and I will be in Bay Area tomorrow, maybe we can met. I will text you.
Suibi Weng: And then, Amy? Thank you, Amy, she's my quantitative method teacher. And I always remember that we're working on our IEEEVR paper till 5 AM, with Turing, and Rishi was in India, and…
Suibi Weng: And, Amy has a soccer game, like, next day.
Suibi Weng: And she's so nice, just stay here and helping us with the paper. And, I mean, I recommend that if you need a committee, just looking for Amy. Yeah, and Netta was there, I don't know why.
Suibi Weng: Okay, okay.
Suibi Weng: Thanks, Leo and Daniel. You two are my all-time hero, for sure. And I think it's an honor that working both of you, and…
Suibi Weng: I think I was always bragging that I'm working with Leo Suzuki and Daniel Leginker in the same room, but in different times. Amazing thing. I hope one day I can reach out to your level, but we'll see. Thank you.
Suibi Weng: And, oh, Mark, is Mark here?
Suibi Weng: Okay, nevermind. Mark is here, and I want to thank Mark, because I think Atlas is a really special place for me, and I think for all of us, thank you for his directions and his vision, and thank Mark? Okay.
Suibi Weng: Oh, next one is my family, okay, this is my mom, this is my dad. This is a picture that before I came to United States, there's a dinner, and kind of like.
Suibi Weng: Yeah, so… I forgot what to say. Okay, so, actually, my English is, influenced by my dad, because when I was, like, 6 years old or something, my dad wanted practicing his English, so he was reading out the English version of Sherlock Holmes.
Suibi Weng: It's next to me, and then translate it into Chinese or Taiwanese, and just, like, helping me to understand English. I don't know, probably he just wants to practice, okay?
Suibi Weng: And my mom actually, she inspired me a lot of ways, and one of the biggest inspi- inspirations is she finished her undergrad when she was almost 45 years old. It was a university next to Ellen's high school.
Suibi Weng: So…
Suibi Weng: So, she… her… her major was special education, and it's a nice school, so she had to bring me to there. And the professor just saw the kid sitting over there, they are educational professor, right? Sitting over there, they were so exciting, like, oh, there's a kid over there, so let me try out some… my theory to you, like…
Suibi Weng: They put out a mental rotation or something, like, and they say, can you do that? No, they're like, yeah, this kid, his brain is not developed enough to do nothing.
Suibi Weng: Yes. Thank you, Professor.
Suibi Weng: And the last one is my aunt. She's the professor in Tainan Art University. She was my babysitter, and she encouraged me to doing my PhD and a lot of things, and thank you for that. And her PhD thesis is about heavy metal music.
Suibi Weng: Something like that, but, it's writing in French, so… French, so I cannot really read it.
Suibi Weng: Okay, thank you for my family.
Suibi Weng: Next one is you guys! Yay! So, thank you, everyone coming here today, and it is a blast to… working with you, and, to hanging out with you.
Suibi Weng: complain something with you, and I think I came here, I don't have friend… I mean, I have friend in California, no one living in Denver, right? So, thank you for your companion, and…
Suibi Weng: Thank you, thank you, thank you. And I want to shout out to my cohort, I think it's, is David here?
Suibi Weng: Yay, David! And is Deanna my call right now?
Suibi Weng: You both are going to do your defense, you're definitely better than this, so… I'm not sure, I'm not sure I will be here for you guys, because I'm not sure where am I, actually. But, all the best, you will do…
Suibi Weng: do the really good defense. And shout out to my cohort, Dr. Rishi and Dr. Krasik.
Suibi Weng: You guys will conquer the world, for sure. These two is the best, and hopefully one day you conquer the world, just leave a tiny piece for me. Yeah, thank you so much. Okay, that's keeping, set, connect, and keeping sending mean to each other, and…
Suibi Weng: If we are in the same city, please text me, I will try my best to show up, or I will write a really long text, and with a two crying face at the end.
Suibi Weng: Thank you so much!
Suibi Weng: Right?
Suibi Weng: Let me turn on the lights, actually, I think… Do we need… yeah.
Suibi Weng: Yay! Wow! Okay, that's light.
Suibi Weng: Yeah, any question in… Yeah, sure.
Suibi Weng: It's okay. Yeah.
Suibi Weng: Moves on to ask the question.
Suibi Weng: I would… Yeah. Appreciate it.
Suibi Weng: Especially at the end, you were mentioning how
Suibi Weng: the struggle matters, and the feeling of saying, wow, I made it worth is important. What would you say was the moment you thought about these projects that made you feel that disturbance?
Suibi Weng: Your most struggleest? Oh, strongest. That you thought was… that made you feel the best about making it and making all that from together? I think it's the last project, the hypervisions, because this is something, in my mind, is… I always want to try to…
Suibi Weng: And, the whole project, the result or something is astonishing. Like, oh.
Suibi Weng: Oh, that's actually work, although there's some… some flaws about that, but I think that generally makes me feel like I'm capable to finish up this, research project, yeah.
Suibi Weng: I'm afraid, hello.
Suibi Weng: If you build a tool, instead of hypervision, it's hypervision.
Suibi Weng: Are they interested?
Suibi Weng: Yeah.
Suibi Weng: in lower quality, something in the tempo.
Suibi Weng: You can imagine if that would have any meaningful qualities?
Suibi Weng: So, actually, even the hypervision I show is in a pretty low quality, because we don't have a really good, what? What happened? Oh, sorry. So,
Suibi Weng: Netta was asking if the hypervision in a really low quality, result, if… can I imagine what kind of system will…
Suibi Weng: 10 miles, right, yeah.
Suibi Weng: So, actually, in Hypervision, because you saw the video, it's kind of looking really good, but…
Suibi Weng: the resolution or the transformation flicking around actually is the low quality in this time. So.
Suibi Weng: I can share one thing as what… how I frame this work. It's actually, I'm kind of avoiding those quality-changing things, but even that, a lot of user or participants, they try it
Suibi Weng: they really like it, because they never feel… never have this kind of experience, like, oh, your whole vision is being taken out for the generative AI. Of course, if there's a better quality in the future, they probably will compare, so, wow, your thing is
Suibi Weng: Like, shit. But I think for now, because it's a novel interaction, so people think, oh, that's really cool, and they will think about how to… working on it.
Suibi Weng: Aye. Can I… For the… when you're doing, like.
Suibi Weng: full AI, like, for what you're seeing, if you're looking out into the room. Yeah. If you…
Suibi Weng: Is there, like, enough stability in what you're creating that you could do a re-render for, like, each eye to actually get, like, the depth perception?
Suibi Weng: Yes, and… Okay, do I need to, repeat the question? Yes, so, Sawyer is asking, like, is there possible to stabilize the generative frame?
Suibi Weng: Basically, yeah. And, or, or in each… each in each ice. So, the question is…
Suibi Weng: I'm gonna answer that really… probably a really bad way, is that technically, if we have a really strong graphic car, the… the…
Suibi Weng: the generated result. I mean, throughout all my projects, the generated result will be perfect. But again, I mean, I'm working around those systems, and…
Suibi Weng: Even the generative result is not good enough, but I think in the user study, we still can think about the possibility that if that's going that great.
Suibi Weng: And for the two eyes question, again, it's like, if you're gonna rendering two times, then it's like double time of the rendering and double time of computation. Totally doable.
Suibi Weng: But… Yeah, Indian money. Yes.
Suibi Weng: Thank you.
Suibi Weng: I think we can move to…
Suibi Weng: Is anyone on… online has a question?
Suibi Weng: I like most of your commuting?
Suibi Weng: Yeah.
Suibi Weng: Okay, then that's perfect. Okay.
Suibi Weng: But something… someone's saying something in the chat?
Suibi Weng: So you're on the side with… Yeah. Daniel? Yeah, sure.
Suibi Weng: But actually, Daniel and Tom is, like… Equally away.
Suibi Weng: Daniel can go first, I think, yeah.
Daniel Leithinger: Alright, sounds good.
Daniel Leithinger: Yeah.
Suibi Weng: Hello.
Daniel Leithinger: Yeah, thanks for your presentation.
Daniel Leithinger: I have a question about… so, when you interact with these systems.
Daniel Leithinger: A lot of this… it is prompt-based.
Daniel Leithinger: And… When you were showing Dream Portal, you were showing mostly text prompting?
Suibi Weng: Yes.
Daniel Leithinger: The question for me would be…
Daniel Leithinger: You've experimented with other modalities of prompting?
Daniel Leithinger: Okay. Like, using visual inputs, or… since you are in mixed reality and interacting with it, what… what is your…
Daniel Leithinger: Take on, for instance, using gestures or other modalities?
Suibi Weng: Okay.
Suibi Weng: Thank you. So, I mean, in Dream Proto, because we are testing… kind of like testing out the ability of how LLM can generate the behavior, so we focus on the text only.
Suibi Weng: However, I won't say just only text, because it's… before we send everything to LLM, we still, kind of attach the field, oh, sorry, the scene's information. For example, there's a table over there, there's, there's other virtual objects in the scene. So, it's not just only user's prompt.
Suibi Weng: But I think, in the other project, like Editing Reality, we're actually trying just using Sketch as another prompting method. So I think there will be really interesting, like, combine those different modalities together. And I will say there's one tiny part I try to do, but it's not doing that well, is I want to inquire the
Suibi Weng: space informations to… into the DreamProto generations, but I think because we are using prompt engineering, it's not good enough for now, so the generation sometimes is still off, and it's not stable, yeah.
Suibi Weng: But I think that's a really good idea, like, we can think about the other modality in this system.
Suibi Weng: Does that answer? Question?
Daniel Leithinger: Yeah, sure, thank you.
Suibi Weng: Thank you!
Daniel Leithinger: I don't know if we want to go around and circle back, or…
Suibi Weng: Yeah.
Daniel Leithinger: ask all questions at once. Ellen, what's your take on that?
Suibi Weng: Yeah, but we kept keeping asking questions, I think. We want Daniel to ask a whole bunch of questions before we go on to the next one, or do we want to do it wrong? Like, he asks one question, Tom asks one question, and he asks… Oh, I think…
Suibi Weng: Daniel can continue it. Yeah, continue asking questions. Yes, then Daniel, you can… asking questions.
Daniel Leithinger: So, I, I, had one question about hypervision, and that was, so, you were mentioning already, I don't know if I fully understood the previous question. Yes.
Daniel Leithinger: By the audience, we mentioned about the visual quality, and I remember in the video, there was a lot of flickering between objects and warping between them.
Daniel Leithinger: Yes. What was that? You were saying something about graphics cards performance, but…
Suibi Weng: Yes, elaborate.
Daniel Leithinger: A little bit on that?
Suibi Weng: Yes, so that's… so the… the string model we use is called string diffusions, and actually what you say… seen in the… in the video, the quality or the resolution actually only, I think is 512 and…
Suibi Weng: And 512, so these are really small, small resolutions.
Suibi Weng: And because we want to hit up the FPS to 30%, 30 FPS, I mean, it's still slow, so you can see the quality is not, not consistently.
Suibi Weng: But I did saw someone with using the better graphic card and better scenes that they can hit on, like, 10 FPS, but in a really stable, just not flicking around system. But, however, that's still… it's kind of like a balance, like, if you want quality, then you need a really good
Suibi Weng: good hardware, but then your FPS getting low.
Suibi Weng: then the FPS getting low, then you cannot really fully immersive in the hypervision experience, yeah. But… but again, I think that's… that's not the really, the target I want to focus on current project, because I think, yeah, probably next year, there will be a better graphic card, better technique, can solve that, so I…
Suibi Weng: I framed that paper as, like, oh, even equality is not that good, so how can you re… reimagine nation, like.
Suibi Weng: If this pro- project is going…
Suibi Weng: extremely well, then what kind of, scenario you can come up? Yeah.
Daniel Leithinger: No, that's totally reasonable. I mean, we all expect hardware to become faster, and software as well. One question as to, with the user study you were mentioning, when people noticed that, I would imagine it would be highly disruptive
Daniel Leithinger: Is it possible to even, run a proper comparison or study?
Daniel Leithinger: When there's things that are super low res and flickering the whole time.
Suibi Weng: I think… actually, the interesting thing is, people…
Suibi Weng: I think people kind of not really addressing the flickering is that disturbing, because, like I just mentioned, it's like, this is a totally new experience. So, they did not know what the stable vision look like.
Suibi Weng: So they think, oh, that's really cool, and that's following the structure, and that probably
Suibi Weng: still anchor on some, RGB image or something like that. So, the funny thing is, like, they did not really, really feel that it's disturbing. They think it's really interesting and really inspiring. However, I…
Suibi Weng: if we're gonna move forward to kind of really seriously testing this result, I would say.
Suibi Weng: we can bring another, video… video-to-video real-time generation software and to… to try out how people think differently, like using hypervision, and compare a more stable, visual to do that. Or just using a pre-rendering 360 video and compare to VR.
Suibi Weng: Yeah, something like that.
Daniel Leithinger: That's really, really interesting. I also… I would love to learn just briefly what user input you did with the… with… with hypervision, like.
Daniel Leithinger: As people are saying, I want to remove or add, like, how did… how did the prompting work out there?
Suibi Weng: Okay, so in hypervision, we actually introduced a couple interaction things. First of all is sketching. You can draw in stuff.
Daniel Leithinger: huh?
Suibi Weng: And the second thing is applying a mask into a real object, and you can see the real object being applied by mask and changing to the different things. And actually, we did a lot of, like, virtual object insert in the hypervision. For example, we actually tried the particle system and tried, like, different animation, like, an animal or human…
Suibi Weng: human in here, but I think the most important, interesting way is people using different physical material to try out a hypervision. For example, like, Diana tried using the clay, like, shapeable clay in hypervision, and she should make a flower, and…
Suibi Weng: you can see it re-rendering to a flower, and you can change the prompt and see… I can say, oh, a Star Wars-style flower, and you can see the flower become BBA, or something like that, yeah.
Suibi Weng: So I think that's a… I think the physical interaction is actually more important, or more interesting, yeah, in that sense.
Daniel Leithinger: I was hoping for that. Well, thank you very much, and…
Suibi Weng: Thank you.
Daniel Leithinger: Pass it on to Tom.
Prof. Tom Yeh: Hi, it's… I really like your projected a sense of maturity as a scholar in your presentation, and full of confidence in explaining the materials, and this pretty good job. I think we'll be proud of you going out to represent our university as a PhD.
Prof. Tom Yeh: not a candidate anymore, as an awardee at some point. And also, you… I like how you started with the story of how you,
Prof. Tom Yeh: you tried out the MR device for the first time, and also ChatGPT, and your study has been also tracking the… how the large watch model has evolved over the past few years, very quickly. And so, I would like you to comment on, from what you've been hearing from users, the change in terms of the perception of… about your work as people go
Prof. Tom Yeh: our word from, like, oh, I never heard of, I couldn't even spell… I couldn't even spell GPT. GTP? G-GTP? Dude, everybody knows ChatGPT, you don't have to explain what prompt engineering. So have you… I wonder if you're coming on the… the progression of the user's perception of your system as a result of the…
Prof. Tom Yeh: Increased familiarity of it.
Prof. Tom Yeh: AI.
Prof. Tom Yeh: Generally AI in general, so… have you… are you able to track the changes?
Suibi Weng: Okay, I think I more… I think I can tackle this, problem with more user expecting, user perspective, because I feel like there's a two-way to say that, is the one way is the generations difference, because
Suibi Weng: Personally feeling…
Suibi Weng: our grandchildren will think sending email is totally need to be generated. Like, we don't have to writing by ourselves, everything should be just generated, or something like that. And…
Suibi Weng: And… but for us, because I did do, Leo, Leo's, research.
Suibi Weng: user study, I really feel not comfortable, like, using Cloud AI to write me an email and sending to some real person. I feel like that's really scary.
Suibi Weng: And I think that kind of thing is really just the generation problem. I think after next generation, they will say, that's fine, it should be ChatGPT to take over it.
Suibi Weng: And the other, other way to take… see in it is, last time I talked to David about one thing, it's like.
Suibi Weng: I feel like I coding with generative AI together, it made me feel angrier.
Suibi Weng: like…
Suibi Weng: just why AI just doesn't listen to me, even though that's not my code. But that kind of emotion never happening when I coding by myself. And I think that's a really interesting thing, and I think,
Suibi Weng: you kind of have more emotional burden when you talk to generative AI, because it's just keeping back and forth, back and forth, and nothing just really works.
Suibi Weng: That could be fixed later, but what I'm trying to say in this dissertation is
Suibi Weng: I don't think generated AI take over those efforts.
Suibi Weng: Generated AI should introduce a nature way to interact with systems.
Suibi Weng: We are not… I mean, the really good thing for ChatGPT is we are not inventing a new language to talk to AI model, it's we just using chat box to talk to them. So, Gen AI should
Suibi Weng: reveal ourself or reconnect our expression back to ourself. For example, if you are a painter.
Suibi Weng: the prompting should be sketch. If you are musicians, the prompting should be using your instrument, or you should sing it. And that's… I think that's the power of generative AI. It's not take over the effort, it's like, let us reconnect to our human nature. Yeah.
Prof. Tom Yeh: Also, can you also comment about the XR? So, XR, the MR hardware that's probably not changing as fast as, GEM AI, and, so there's probably one or two pieces of hardware coming out each year, instead of, like…
Prof. Tom Yeh: 200 models for each year.
Prof. Tom Yeh: So, what, what do, what do you see, People also, like, becoming…
Prof. Tom Yeh: Are they becoming more receptive, or less receptive of, mixed Reality Hardware.
Suibi Weng: I feel like…
Suibi Weng: Okay, so because I'm in this industry for many years, I have some feeling of the mixed reality, it's like…
Suibi Weng: Over the years, they cannot find killer applications, actually, and that's kind of sad.
Suibi Weng: I think it's only working with, you can say, like, a really specific, workforce, like, for example, military, or for fixing things, or in the construction workers, something like that. But they cannot find a really,
Suibi Weng: better application to… to allows everyone to really have to using VR for every day.
Suibi Weng: However, I think Meta, they find… find a way, try to promote that, is using the Raybon glasses, and using the AI assistant. That could be a changing, but however, for me, as a really deeper
Suibi Weng: XR person, I don't think that's an XR, but I think that's… the experience is, like, it kind of extends from XR, because everything we see, everything we interact is connected with the bigger, ubiquitous computing system. Yeah, so…
Prof. Tom Yeh: Yeah, I have one more quick question. So what do you think about the, you know how AI agents becoming really powerful, and with CloudBot, and so on, and now they have a social network for them, they just talk to each other. A social network used to be for humans, now they are for agents. So I wonder whether you can see a future, near future, the, robots actually wearing MR devices so that your app is
Prof. Tom Yeh: actually could help robots. Like, can you comment on that?
Prof. Tom Yeh: just follow my thought and develop. This is not a fully developed thought at all, I just want to prompt you.
Suibi Weng: What do you distingu.
Prof. Tom Yeh: Goodbye.
Prof. Tom Yeh: So, no, no.
Prof. Tom Yeh: Yeah, so you're not… you're not in front of ChatGPT right now, so I could… whatever you say right now is genuine, so I want to hear, but given my prompt, can you complete my prompt? I just complete… complete my prompt. The… imagine the future when the robot wearing your MR devices, what does it mean?
Suibi Weng: Actually…
Suibi Weng: I think you mentioned a really interesting point, is can we transfer our human senses to those generative AI agents?
Suibi Weng: And I think that probably…
Suibi Weng: Leo Ma gonna do that? I know you're not kidding! He… so, I think it's like…
Suibi Weng: Because now, the language model talking to each other, there's still, like, really cold, machines talking to each other. If we introduce some humanity into that community, what will become, and what kind of new…
Suibi Weng: scenario will show up. And actually, talking about agentic AI, actually, this is really interesting, because when I'm talking about editing reality.
Suibi Weng: I used negotiate, and Alan was nagging about me, like, what does that mean, negotiate? Negotiate should be like a bargain chip or something, but, you know.
Suibi Weng: currently generate, Agent AI cost token. So, the thing is, like, when I'm trying to create something, and that's… bargain chip is the token, is really vivid in there. And, yeah, back to your question, I think…
Suibi Weng: I think we can provide general agent more sensor, or the other perspective, but it's more, like, from human perspective, and I think that would be really interesting, yeah.
Prof. Tom Yeh: Okay, I'll pass on the next committee member. Thank you.
Suibi Weng: Yay. Amy?
Amy Banic: Yes, so thank you, Sweebe, for, the… your framework. I really think it's comprehensive from virtual content generation, behavioral.
Amy Banic: Generation, and then the perceptual, so that was a really nice…
Amy Banic: Story to tell, for those elements.
Amy Banic: My question… well, I have a couple questions, but one of them…
Amy Banic: Is related to your research question, where, you ask.
Amy Banic: how do users engage in co-creative processes with generative MR systems? And, specifically how these systems scaffold iteration, exploration, and refinement. And I think you did a great job of
Amy Banic: kind of demonstrating that through these three systems. My question is, did you notice in any of your evaluations, potentially, if there was any moments where the interaction or the prompt
Amy Banic: Engineering, or how people were interacting with those systems hindered that co-creative process.
Suibi Weng: Sorry, what's a hinger?
Amy Banic: Oh, sorry, maybe negatively impacted. So you gave, actually, one example where you feel angry, sometimes you…
Suibi Weng: Yes, huh.
Amy Banic: coding with AI.
Suibi Weng: Yes.
Amy Banic: When people were working with your systems, did you notice anything, like, like, for example, maybe in the.
Suibi Weng: perception.
Amy Banic: transformation. It was a little too much, and it became distracting, or something like that. Was there any point where maybe this was not good for creative processes?
Suibi Weng: Yes, so one of the things… okay, so I think hypervision, the disrupt, the flicking around problem and the glitching.
Suibi Weng: Again, I think people's kind of used to it. There's a couple participants actually complaining about that, for sure, and they say, can I save it? Save the current transformation, and then I can reference later? I did not do that.
Suibi Weng: That function, because I'm lazy. But, however.
Suibi Weng: Actually, you mentioned one thing about the disturb. It's happening in the editing reality, because
Suibi Weng: couple function is taking so long. For example, like, retexturing took, like, 10 minutes to do retexturing, and people just wearing a headset and sitting there and waiting everything, and the other thing is, like, this couple other function is not doing that well.
Suibi Weng: In that paper, actually, I mentioned about the waiting time, and actually, I… I claim that the waiting… waiting mechanism is a really part, important in the generated system, because no matter what, I mean, yes, one day, good graphic card can fix that.
Suibi Weng: One day, but it still has the waiting… waiting process. So, our suggestion in that… that, certain point is, like, you can have a preview image or some visual… visual loading image to… to kind of let people know, oh, the system's still working, and then you don't have to wait for 10 minutes, you can work on different pipelines and different things.
Suibi Weng: So, again, I think…
Suibi Weng: System should suggest that, if there's a waiting or there's a delay, system should suggest that, okay, you can move on to the other task, something like that.
Amy Banic: Okay, thank you. And then, so this…
Amy Banic: This refers to one of your other research questions, where you talk about, what interaction modalities best support
Amy Banic: These types of processes, and,
Amy Banic: some of what I could gather is not necessarily that you found what interaction modalities best support, but, you know, what's feasible in this space, it seems to me that that's what you've found.
Amy Banic: given that, and this kind of ties into maybe what Daniel was talking about a little bit.
Amy Banic: in that you're in the immersive environment, whether that's in the VR system or in the AR mixed reality system.
Amy Banic: What.
Suibi Weng: We can hear you.
Amy Banic: Yeah, I, I paused for a second, sorry, sweetie.
Amy Banic: I muted myself.
Amy Banic: So I guess what I'm getting at is when you're in the, mixed reality, situation or system,
Amy Banic: When we're thinking about interaction modalities and, you know, you looked at some gesturing where you were sketching, you looked at, some
Amy Banic: Language models, so prompt-based.
Amy Banic: What would you redesign, going forward, in the interaction modalities that could better provide that co-collaboration with the AI agent that maybe is more situated for
Amy Banic: text-based systems, or web-based systems, and maybe not necessarily XR.
Suibi Weng: Yeah.
Suibi Weng: So, I feel like that's, inquire more…
Suibi Weng: So, I think that's two things. One is, we have to think, what kind of scenario we have to build, and what kind of users that they are more nature to do the prompting. The example I just mentioned is, like, if you are a musician, then you should use your instrument or your music to do the prompting. And if
Suibi Weng: If that's the case, then the whole prompting scenario will follow in
Suibi Weng: that modality to create. And the second thing is, I feel like, currently, prompt testing system is like, I say one line and you say something, something like that.
Suibi Weng: But I… I think we should think more about, like, how do you make this, process, well, be more, fluent, and, like, let people stay in the action perception loop, that you can create something and
Suibi Weng: with that frame, then you can create other things on the top of it. But that really depends on different tasks, because if we are talking about music… music creation, then that will be… that… that won't be using visual input. It could be, like, using sound, or using vibration, something like that, but I think that's a really
Suibi Weng: interesting question, and I… in one of the claims in the paper is, I said, we should keep
Suibi Weng: user in that loop, and they can create more things. Yeah. So, system should invite them to talk to the system, to interact more. Yep.
Amy Banic: So, that's more on these,
Amy Banic: XR side, what about the, AI algorithm side? What… what will you… potentially recommend
Amy Banic: changes to, like, let's say the large language models, or how people are modeling these algorithms to better support XR interaction with these agents.
Suibi Weng: Yes.
Suibi Weng: Honestly saying, because a lot of this project is building, like, last year or two years ago.
Suibi Weng: Currently, Agentech AI come out, and actually, I mean, the Dream Proto should apply to the Agentech AI, and I haven't tried it to see what's gonna improve with Agentech AI. So,
Suibi Weng: But again, I think there's a… there's a misunderstanding, or I… because I personally, I haven't really heavily tried the agentic AI things, but…
Suibi Weng: It supposedly can have a better, better memory and better structure when you're trying to
Suibi Weng: coding, or making the scenes, planning, or other things. So…
Suibi Weng: That's probably the next step I will try, not just only using API call to ChatGPT or Gemini, and try on how can we set up a small agentic AI and to do this, this specific
Suibi Weng: Task, yeah.
Suibi Weng: Thank you.
Amy Banic: Okay, thank you, and I pass the baton.
Amy Banic: The virtual baton.
Suibi Weng: Beautiful.
Suibi Weng: So, where's the bind?
Suibi Weng: Oh, you can… Oh, so should I mute it?
Suibi Weng: We can hear you.
Suibi Weng: Wait, wait, wait, wait, I can mute it, I can mute it. Yeah.
Ellen Do: All right, now I turn on my… But that's slowly, slowly, slowly.
Suibi Weng: AI cannot help us do not.
Suibi Weng: Yeah. Okay, cool. I push it.
Suibi Weng: So that, first of all, a couple of comments on the documents, and I guess it's pretty…
Suibi Weng: input from the proposal, which is… Oh, thank you!
Suibi Weng: Yeah.
Suibi Weng: The… on the section 4… Yeah.
Suibi Weng: Yeah, I… Also, I don't really have any kind of screenshot for the figures, or… it's pretty thin. Yes. Even though…
Suibi Weng: I was gonna spend a lot of time on, kind of, you know, iterating it. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, why do you call it a proposed system as,
Suibi Weng: Because, okay, so the first thing is, yeah, you know what happened to that. So, I think we have a lot of, struggling in that project, and…
Suibi Weng: Actually, originally, I want to make, I want to finish up and do the user study, but it's just not there, so… Yes, yes.
Suibi Weng: I, I know I can write a report, yes. So the proposed system. Yeah, so you can also be, another one.
Suibi Weng: Unnoticed. So, okay, okay.
Suibi Weng: Bob, yeah, you can do that. Okay.
Suibi Weng: In the slide, you had, some in some of the demos. Yes. But it's also not shown in the document, so… Yeah, okay. I can put that back.
Suibi Weng: Thank you.
Suibi Weng: I just have a couple questions regarding. Yeah. So you said, this is a partner? Yeah. Partner. Partner, yes, yes. Partner to a tool.
Suibi Weng: But how do you define coloring? What's the difference between function? That… Specifically for… Yes.
Suibi Weng: I feel like we… so, the claim I want to try to say…
Suibi Weng: Probably not saying that well in the presentation or document, it's like…
Suibi Weng: I don't want just try, treat generative AI model as a tool.
Suibi Weng: And it's something we can interact with and discuss with. So I think that's kind of dynamic. It's a partner relationship. It's like, it can give me the feedback, or it can help me to build something. It's not just, like, I input
Suibi Weng: bunch of numbers, and you give me the output. So that's the partnership, I think, to think about. The essence of the essence of differentiating between partners and tools. I feel like it's the interaction. Yeah, interaction, and also the randomness.
Suibi Weng: that AI… AI model provides. Because I think that's important, because if without randomness or the… the not consistent generation, then AI model just a formula, like, oh, I put… I change…
Suibi Weng: minus 2, and you give me minus A, something like that. But you can see how we interact with AI model is, like, it can… it can have a little bit randomness and a little bit unpredictable… unpredictable, between our conversations, yeah.
Suibi Weng: Do you call, for example, Sora with a partner? Sora? Sora.
Suibi Weng: I was as a partner.
Suibi Weng: Because… because there's one thing I keep on saying is the negotiation, because the generation result is not totally… how do you say? Sometimes generation result is not what we want.
Suibi Weng: And every time, even I try to draw the… draw the graph in the presentation, I send it to AI, and just missing some line, and you're keeping asking, then…
Suibi Weng: how I did it is, like, then you just give me the frame, and I put those into… in Figma. So… so I think that's the part of the negotiation happens, yeah. And you cannot negotiate with a system, because systems say.
Suibi Weng: what it is, just like that. And the second question is, in the title, you said, AI generated user experience. Yes.
Suibi Weng: But… I think type of video might be okay, but editing reality, or… Or Binproto.
Suibi Weng: I'm also here at D.
Suibi Weng: content for the same, but what do you mean by AI-generated user experience? Because what I feel like, okay, we can change. But, okay, I got that. So the thing, yeah, become… more become confessed.
Suibi Weng: So, what I feel is, like, the interaction or the generative asset is a part of the user experience. That's how I… how I think about that, so why I… so, I will say the whole… even just asset, or just interaction, because in the DreamPortal, actually, I mentioned, like.
Suibi Weng: the… User experience is not just only
Suibi Weng: object is only… is including the interaction. So, this, forward to user experience. That's why I choose the topic, and ChatGPT helped a little bit.
Suibi Weng: Okay.
Suibi Weng: Yeah,
Suibi Weng: I'm not sure I want to ask the third question. Yeah, you can ask, what is this used for, or, you know, in terms of…
Suibi Weng: I feel like you're kind of making… inventing a new media. Yeah. Yeah, but we don't have an idea.
Suibi Weng: So, for example, it's hard to define. I mean, hard to imagine coming down, but you are, making the books out of, like, printing press. Yeah. And it's hard to imagine, like, what Shakespeare writes on him. Oh… It's… I… it's honestly, like, it's hard… Yeah. …to predict.
Suibi Weng: what it's gonna be used for, who it's gonna use for, but still, I'm kind of thinking about it in your ideal situation. Yeah.
Suibi Weng: What do you envision the future of…
Suibi Weng: What do you envision a fleet board in the future?
Suibi Weng: Nikki. Okay. So, one of the things, for example, like.
Suibi Weng: I mean, I kind of mentioned about our last project of hypervision, because that's probably more futuristic.
Suibi Weng: Upon three of them. I think, at the end of paper, I actually mentioned, like, there's some future research question we can use in this system to tackle on.
Suibi Weng: For example, I can change people into different avatars or different scenes, and we can use that as a tool to investigate it, like, the trust between
Suibi Weng: human and AI, that's one thing. The second thing is, like, we can try on, like, for example, like, perception research.
Suibi Weng: Oh, sorry. Redirecting walking, I can change my corridor, like, change to the curve line, or something like that, if the model is stable enough. That's, like, two of the things. I try to, reconnect back to the MR research question. Yeah, something like that.
Suibi Weng: And also, like, different perspective, like, I can change my cup to… to a rat, or something like that, then you can have a different sensation on this, yeah. That question makes me wonder…
Suibi Weng: Why? Why? Yeah, why? I feel like as I tried to… because, like, really, years ago, I'm kind of really interesting in doing, like, perception in mixed reality and XR, so…
Suibi Weng: We mentioned about the Lead Away, the robot dog, that project is actually doing the redirecting working, so I…
Suibi Weng: Kinda interesting, like, how you're hacking the people's sensation, so there's a one…
Suibi Weng: tiny part of me want to do that. So I reconnect that project to that part, yeah. You're not actually hacking people's sensation, their perception.
Suibi Weng: Good. Good call. Yes.
Suibi Weng: physical world, but you're actually not modifying the physical world. You're not making the physical object appear, you're making the perception of the physical world change. Yes. So a lot of times you say, editing reality and changing the physical world. No, they're still there. I just cut the… You walk over there, it will be…
Suibi Weng: Trip, yeah, trip it. No, don't make them feel.
Suibi Weng: Yeah. I think that's probably why I do it.
Suibi Weng: Generated. Oh, but I put yours.
Suibi Weng: Okay, can we change it? Because I think if I was using generating realities to overclean…
Suibi Weng: Oh, okay.
Suibi Weng: a lot of times just say, I'm changing the physical reality. No, you did not. Yeah. You're tricking people, believing the physical reality changed, but that's actually not there. Okay. And so, actually, all the way you're doing it, you are hacking people's perceptions, actions.
Suibi Weng: Yes.
Suibi Weng: Exactly. Thank you, Judge.
Suibi Weng: in a different way. Yes. And I was thinking about in whatever the professor feels.
Suibi Weng: Ada?
Suibi Weng: Okay.
Suibi Weng: Thank you.
Suibi Weng: Thank you so much. Does the community want to have more questions, just with Sydney, or are we ready to have a scope?
Suibi Weng: So, I should stop the recording? No, no, I'm waiting for them to… Oh, you muted.
Suibi Weng: Oh, wow. Can you hear, Alan?
Amy Banic: Yeah, I'm okay.
Suibi Weng: Yeah.
Suibi Weng: if we are okay, then maybe we kick everybody out. Yeah. Do people have more questions for CB?
Suibi Weng: No, stop. You can ask later, though.
Suibi Weng: Oh.
Suibi Weng: Okay, thank you.
Suibi Weng: Am I gonna stay here, or… no, I should go out.
Suibi Weng: Does any of the committee members want Sui to stay in the room?
Suibi Weng: Okay, stop recording, stop recording. Oh, bless you.